so i was wondering if we can talk about
mindfulness of breathing
in terms of what the venerable arita
has said mindfulness breathing is the
mindfulness of breathing that he does
in the suitors
so on one occasion
the blessed one asked monks do you
develop mindfulness of in and out
breathing and when this was said venable arita
and when this was said venable arita
replied to the blessed one i developed
mindfulness of in and out breathing lord
but how do you develop such mindfulness
and arita replies
having abandoned sensual desire for past
sensual pleasures having done away with
sensual desire for
future sensual pleasures and having
thoroughly subdued perceptions of
resistance with regard to internal and external
with regard to internal and external
events
i breathe in mindfully and i breathe out
mindfully so the buddha says that there is that
so the buddha says that there is that
kind of
there is that mindfulness of breathing i
don't say that there isn't
but as to how mindfulness of in and out
breathing is brought
in detail to its condemnation listen and
pay close attention i will speak
and then he goes in the classic uh
description right right
but so what i'm interesting is is
irita's mindfulness his description
well i think the um the bit to mention
there is
i think some people might think that
arita was wrong with something
that what he described is not correct
mindfulness with reading and then the
buddha gave him the right one but that's not
gave him the right one but that's not
what it says he says yeah what you said
is right
it is mindfulness of breathing
but it's not complete venerable at it as
mindfulness of reading
can certainly well certainly helped him
free himself from centrality factually
because we just didn't say oh you're not
free from centrality and that's not
mindfulness of bleeding which you
described he just said that's fine but let me give
he just said that's fine but let me give
you the detail
that results in combination of that
practice so it's just not enough
for for our engines so like you need to
go into a bit more detail
which then also makes you realize that
venerable arita described
was is sufficient to make you onigami so
if you practice mindfulness for
breathing even in that simple sense that
he described
which is by the way how every
mindfulness of breathing formulation
does start
mindful knowingly he breathes in
knowingly he breathes out
that's all you need to know and if you
stick to that as vulnerable editor did
you will lose you will overcome any um
desire those essential pleasures now of
the past
for the future in other words you you
would have surmounted the entire domain
of of um of central craving
and most importantly you would have
completely subdued that fatigue
resistance or aversion towards your own
senses and so on that we spoke in
previous videos and that's
obviously as venerable declared enough
for the five love effects to be
destroyed
so for the complete arghantrip then the
buddha gives a further description of
where you get i don't know
like give specific descriptions because
people are already way too much taking
anapanasati to be a mechanical method
so that's why i think it's actually
better if people follow a venerable
arita's instruction first because it
will prevent you from falling into that
mindless or whatever you've been doing uh and
or whatever you've been doing uh and
force you to to see things on the level
of knowledge
of an enduring breath underneath your
experience like what we said before
regardless of the mind state regardless
of the emotional state
regardless of the physical state that's
why mindfulness of breeding come brings
mindfulness of breeding come brings
satipatanos to fulfillment
mind state emotional state physical
state
but if you start getting into these
details how i will breathe in
like this and i'll do this to the body
formation and on the desk to the body
formation that will all become apparent if you
that will all become apparent if you
become what vanderbilt is there so if
you overcome all the sensuality
subdue all the fatigue you have towards
your own senses
have no your will towards anything or
anyone in the world
past the future then
follow the rest of anapanasati then you
will know exactly what it meant how er
gladdening the body and experience
enjoyable while breathing in or
breathing out you know exactly what it
means but otherwise people would be doing it
but otherwise people would be doing it
with sensuality uh
with with pretty much as something i
should do they will result in even
greater pleasure for me
greater experience any any greatness of
anapanasati on that level
can only be done or can only be
developed on the basis of complete
surmounting of centrality and the final
over factors
but that's for me in a way it's a very
good news
you don't need to worry about every
single little step
if you cultivate and bring to
fulfillment the knowledge of breathing
in
breathing out regardless of the posture
regardless of the emotional state
regardless of the mental state
regardless of the specific thoughts you
have it
that is your anchor that is underneath
your experience that is always enduring
and you don't lose sight of it the
breath the
knowledge of the breath being there not
i'm focusing on the physical side of it
you can focus on the physical side of it
if you want while you know that it's
underneath you for what it is
that's really what the anchor is
so using the the enduring breath it's
already happening to you
underneath your emotional states or
mental states or physical states
as an anchor and investing effort to not
lose the sight of it peripherally to be
aware i don't need to stop doing what i'm
i don't need to stop doing what i'm
doing in order to breathe
but i can certainly not allow myself to
be too absorbed in what i'm doing
so that i forget that i am breathing at
the same time
so it's learning how to not overly
commit to your focusing attention
and actually learn how to stretch your
mind to see like these both ends
to see like these both ends
simultaneously enduring
that's what it would refer to like you
know you develop samadhi the mind
becomes pliable and stretchy not not
like a
hard twisted knotted lump
but so in his description he's he goes
beyond century pleasures sensuality
so if there's virtue and there's
restraint and he's putting up with the pressure
and he's putting up with the pressure
he's enjoying the pressure
whether he's overcome the pressure or
not you know but even if he's putting up
you know but even if he's putting up
with the pressure
not giving into sensuality then he says
subduing um those perceptions
perceptions of resistance resistance
conversion aversion so
and as you're saying you know so you
give up all these
um sensual exploits
things calm down and what you're left
with is uh clearly seeing reality
is uh clearly seeing reality
the reality of your body yeah but see
that reality would present itself first
as this this sort of oxygen as the suits
talk about
in the sense of you're going to
experience almost like physical
physical resistance sickness
like like a heroin addict withdrawing
from the drugs or something you are
withdrawing from the
domain of the entire central being
so it's going to be felt physically but
actually it's not
the physical aspect of it the pain of
that endurance
is your aversion towards it towards the
discomfort but discomfort in itself it's actually
but discomfort in itself it's actually
quite bearable if samadhi has been
developed
that's like if if monk doesn't have the
samadhi in that coming in their proper
sense to
like to use all the calming of the
endurance not to get rid of the
endurance or to base pleasure over it no just to
or to base pleasure over it no just to
calm
the aversion aspect off the same thing
and then yeah my mind is absolutely can
become absolutely boundless
limitless in that sense as as light as
you can imagine
the most agreeable form of experience
within the same endurance because it was
your aversion
that was making it heavy and that's
that's where the work is
in subduing the aversion not in like
psychologizing and trying to justify the
purpose for endurance or why you
shouldn't do it or you should do it or
what you should give in or you shouldn't
give in
all of that means are you still
revolving around basically rooted in a
version no the pure version that you have
no the pure version that you have
towards the non-experience of
non-centrality you have to abandon your
version of it the aversion towards your own
of it the aversion towards your own
senses that are not engaging with
central distractions
and that's why the central distractions
are so powerful
it's because the aversion underneath it
it's it's it's extremely strong
and the only mean of escape from it is
towards sense desires
and you're saying that's your your first
thing so you born you you feel all right right
so you born you you feel all right right
you experience the body yeah
and your first act yeah that's what's
meant by underlying tendencies
they're not there you know the baby is
not doing anything the baby is not
proliferating choosing sensuality but
the baby
its experience its mind is paired with
the senses with the five senses
and they are uncomfortable
however subtly but there is nothing else
there except that discomfort for an
undeveloped mind for a newborn mind
and what an unenlightened mind does
regardless of the type of discomfort and
experience it wants to get rid of it
so naturally on that fundamental level
when the baby is experiencing the
discomfort of its newborn
body and senses is just naturally going
in the direction towards objects
not that he chooses to but the
discomfort pushes it towards you
and then and then everything else it
starts encountering in the world you
know the mother breast feeding just becomes
the mother breast feeding just becomes
like a confirmation of
that direction where it found safety
from this discomfort that
you yourself are this unsafety
because if you just left with the census
but there are five wild animals in the
world and you realize
that's what i am there is nothing else
to me that's the reflections the buddha
will encourage to review this body not
for mechanically see what's anatomically
made of
it's just to see that even the images of
yourself you have are images of this bag
of skin
and it's always any memory you have and
if it involves this bag of skin
these five senses these organs existing
there and that's very unsafe like
and that's very unsafe like
other people have access to your senses
more than you do
and and that's why you're all subversed
towards others as well through the same
process of resistance
but that's a seeing form or your body or
the sixth senses or the elements
for what they are means that you see
them as uncomfortable or
as uncomfortable or
pressured pressured weight yeah you know
pressure burden yeah you will see them
practically speaking you will see them
as a pressure but actually they don't
they don't only there is only pressure
when there is when you're seeing them
with ignorance
which baby does underlying tendency to a
vijay it's not
if if there was no a vj in baby's mind
it wouldn't have been a baby it would
have been born
that's the whole point so that pressure
practically yes that's how you're going
to see them but actually that pressure
is completely gone in another hand
so that pressure is the result of seeing
them with with with
well not clearly with a version with any
other thing that you have not
uh abandoned but if you do see them
clearly if you do see them clearly and if you
if you do see them clearly and if you
sustain the the clarity you will
be unable to to to appropriate them
to own them to even resist them in that
sense because even a version towards
them it's kind of inconceivable
if you clarify it sufficiently enough so
the aversion will fade
so in terms of okay elements sixth sense
body there is a fundamental discomfort
there is a fundamental discomfort
not that you reverse to it sure but
there's a fundamental difference the
body yeah being of that form form like we
yeah being of that form form like we
would have said what is the nature of
uh rupa is or however if you translate
it as form or matter
is nature of form is to deform yeah
that's and that's that's just how it is
that is the nature of the body
which is the elements are constantly
like changing and reshaping and your body is
changing and reshaping and your body is
doing the same
yeah and so that you cannot remove
you cannot just and you can try and you
can kill your body and that doesn't work
okay still stay with the controller it
doesn't work
so you have to kind of appease that
that that creature pees those elements
remember those the vipers
yeah yeah the four great elements that
you have to bathe and so on yeah
well exactly you appease them by
removing your aversion towards them
and it was the same just you reminded me
now when you said the elements and so on
like when that uh when the monk or when
the devil i think was talking to manko
to the buddha
it was about reaching the end of the
world like travels across the universe
to find the end of the elements
and would have said you you doesn't
matter how far you go all you're going
to find is elements
like they're infinite in that sense the
ending of the elements is in with this
own body when there is no more footing
found in your consciousness for them
so when your consciousness sees but when
you cease to appropriate them when you
cease to have lust towards them or
aversion towards them
they will cease they will not pertain to
you anymore
so then truly you reach the end of the universe
universe
erita is doing subduing all
perceptions of how do you do that well
by by
uh
thoroughly developing sense restraint
and then being guarding the dose of the
sense faculties
doesn't mean refusing to see things or
hear things
but means never doing so without being
on god
and that's often where people conflate
like they think guarding the sense
faculties means saying no to everything
i will not look at anything hear
anything i will avoid i will run away if
i start hearing things no no
guarding means you you will have to see
here smell this touch things
so keeping the the the
close eye and the the doorways of your
senses so god in the sense faculties
that's the work so now we're
talking you're you know i'm aware of
what i'm seeing and so on say i hear
something behind
i don't just look without thinking
you want to be aware of your like if you
want to look of your faculty that you're
looking in case of what you see
might induce lust in you or a virgin in
you and that's what would have said he he
and that's what would have said he he
keeps the um
the guard of his he got he sent
faculties and then he doesn't give attention to
and then he doesn't give attention to
any signs and features that arise within
that so say i heard something and i have
an image of what that might be
and based on that image i'll decide
whether i should look or not
and if i have to look then i'll be extra
careful so that when i do look
unwholesome states don't arise in me so
it can sound like oh i have to do a lot
but that's only because you haven't been
guarding the senses properly
people as i said people confuse
gardening we're just refusing to see
refusing to look
no you have to allow some degree of
looking and seeing and
smelling and tasting and touching but
you just always want to be on guard in
regard to that
but my because if you were to uh
kind of crush the body and keep it blind
and not let it hear anything not let it
eat what you know mm-hmm basic amount of
food a little bit of food
hurt the body yes torture it yeah yeah
it's going to be agitated just as
agitated as it would be if you were to
over-indulge exactly exactly so you want to calm
exactly exactly so you want to calm
these wild dogs
well you won't do by giving them what
they want all the time
and you won't do by beating them and
starving them either it will make them
even wilder
more often than not that level of
torture so you need to balance it give them when
so you need to balance it give them when
needed
not unguarded so they don't eat all of
it
or as much as they want but you know
doesn't mean don't give them anything at
all
so i also read about this practice um
it's it's it's called the the element
calming meditation so so for example
meditation so so for example
it would say earth
sun meditation
earth calming meditations and summer
means to bring it back to equilibrium whereby
to bring it back to equilibrium whereby
you're not
agitating this element anymore there is
nothing that you do
that agitates this form these elements
this this body
so the practice of summer not summer as
in the right
right summer as in um
tuned to the right note where is that
practice it's in there when he's described when
it's in there when he's described when
he's teaching uh
rahula how to be right sure
sure and he's teaching him how to subdue
that fatigue really
by calming well yeah that's the suit
about mindfulness for breeding isn't it
wasn't yeah yeah right right
to how to do mindfulness being in regard
to the elements
so you're not doing anything that
agitates yeah
practically speaking you can
[Music] people can see that for themselves for
people can see that for themselves for
example when the body is fatigued
and you're tired you're literally
irritable irritated yeah so there is no reason for
irritated yeah so there is no reason for
you for example
to be illiterate when when the body is
fatigued when body is heavy tight with
the solidity aspect where the element of
earth is felt
more heavier dragging you down or
whatever else
but you are because the mind is not
developed in regard to the body
so that's why you can't just you can't
just count these elements
abstractly you can try but that's not
what the elements are
you are like the basis of elements the
body they found the footing
through your own misconceiving and so on
so when these elements
change when your body
and i don't mean just change in terms of
aging or something but even yeah
sometimes your body feels light
sometimes feels heavy sometimes feels
tired sometimes feels energized
sometimes we're sleepy sometimes awake
sometimes burning sometimes cold
all of those um whatever those that's
what elements are
so you train in regard to that not in
regard to what you perceive elements to
be on account of your body like oh
elements and elements you know
that's you abstractly now just trying to
go through the motions of that
contemplation no no
so mindfully breathing in knowingly
you're breathing in or you're breathing
out underneath this body
what is that body that underneath with
there is breath
how is it felt is it tired is it heavy
is it light
is it aching those are the elements
those are literally the things
you need to develop your mind in regard
to another because tired
i'm averse to that aching i'm averse to
that called
i'm average to that yeah restless guy
restless too much i'm a verse oh that's what
too much i'm a verse oh that's what
aversion is
in regard to me and this body or my
point of view in regards to this body
that's what would have meant for as long
as you're not developed in the body
you will be attracted to sensuality
not developed in the body meaning
meaning you in regard to the body
are not developed but you still have a
version in regard to the discomfort and
by by extension of the same principle
you're going to have lust by
when you experience comfort but it's
actually in regard to
the way the elements are at the time
and that's what it would have said
though there are all those um acid was
to be abandoned simply by enduring them
correctly heat cold insects discomfort burning sun
heat cold insects discomfort burning sun
and so on
words of others abuse of others all of
that is on the level of
you your body being factually assailed
because that's what body is
devoured i mean they said even
the five senses are attacked by
agreeable and disagreeable
ears are attacked by agreeable and
disagreeable sounds that's the nature of
it
that's just between them that's not your
problem but your problem is to have lost towards
but your problem is to have lost towards
agreeable and aversion to disagreeable
so you don't so you remove your last
towards it you remove your aversion
towards it
and then it won't be a problem and
that's the other hand he says
everything that you know all the taints
to be removed i have removed
the being the centrality the ignorance
all that's left
is the disturbances that can arise on
account of this body until it breaks
apart like these natural level of disturbances
so that's you have to be careful if you
want to be doing calming the elements to
not just go into visualizations and so
on
you don't you can't calm the elements on
your own terms because they cannot be
yours you count them by finding what state
you count them by finding what state
they are in now
your body your body is your element
that's why it's often the same use the
word same word rupa for the body rupa
for the elements
that is your practical experience of the
elements
so bringing bringing the elements to
equilibrium what does that mean
that's what we're talking about now but
right well it means that so if
uh like say you might start with the
fatigue naturally to that extent that's how
naturally to that extent that's how
elements present themselves but to you
through your unrestrained senses
you get tired even more unnecessarily so
you sent the
elements even further out of that what
they were naturally
arisen so you you disturb them you
make it even worse or being too averse
towards it you feel even tired than you
actually are
and then you can even come to the point
that you're so averse now
that physically you cease to be tired
yet mentally
you're just naked because of your
aversion not because the elements without
not because the elements without
bringing them back to the natural state
seeing them for whatever reason and not
interfering with it and enduring it
without aversion removing a version towards the
aversion removing a version towards the
endurance of them that's their natural
state but even though their natural state is
but even though their natural state is
not peace and bliss and lovely and
wonderful it's not either yeah dukkha is your
it's not either yeah dukkha is your
interference duke is your aversion
because your last duke is your craving
so yeah that's important to understand
it's not like natural state of the
elements is this you know blissful
mystical realm
no i'm tired naturally the body is tired
didn't eat enough
work too much that is a currently
natural state of these elements
all i need to do is not interfere with
it and endure it mindfully
so then you're seeing the natural
discomfort the natural state yes the natural
the natural state yes the natural
uncomfortable state the natural
uncomfortable state which is not
but it's factually not nice but then you
can then a person can see
the asuba there isn't it
yes yes yeah then it becomes obvious for
what it is you don't need to be lovely
making effort to see it you recognize it
for what it is so this is not
this is not beautiful it's not worth
because it's
well in itself in its natural state it's
it's a burden
it's a it's a it's a weight and
and that's already not nice not
agreeable
it was now if you had to stop there and
stop working well you could
be quite disgusted with that exactly
and that's and so you if you are quite
disgusted with it
means your aversion is taking over not
the natural state
because the natural state has no
aversion nor lust
yet here you are full of aversion
towards that and that's the
way he gave anapanasati because
someone's got two of us
thinking oh this body is truly like that
and they couldn't bear it
but actually no if you calm your mind
you realize no the body is uncomfortable
to that extent
that's it that's where it ends
here and now is pleasant it's very
pleasant arahant arahant's recognition of that
arahant arahant's recognition of that
discomfortable body in its clarity
is the most pleasant experience you can
imagine it's the enlightenment
but if it's aver if it's if it's too
disgusting means
okay so you did probably remove that the
central perception sufficiently
but now you do need to remove your
version of it as well
because you that's not me that's not
going to be anybody so the work
there which i'm jumping and that's
exactly where venus
said that first it was the sensuality
abandoned and what he was left was the
disgust and aversion to his body
these senses and then he subdued that
and now he's just mindfully breathing
and building up
and in i think this is where it goes
into the
subduing of uh perceptions of petiga
is subduing that aversion
in the rahula sutra where the buddhist
teaching in mindfulness and breathing
he goes i think from the asuba realizing
the yasuba there
then practicing brahmavihara which
culminates in upeka which is for the
in upeka which is for the
overcoming of all batiga yeah sure
that's the enlightenment so it's
meta yeah contentment with the whole
thing vegeta
exactly because you don't need to be a
verse that's what i'm saying you realize
the version is coming from me completely
unnecessarily if i remove a version this discomfort
if i remove a version this discomfort
will be blissful
so it's like oh and that's already seen
the mind of friendliness already
um so so that's the again brahmavihara's
another misconceived visualization practice
misconceived visualization practice
starts with a thorough
thorough thoroughfare watchfulness
guarding of the sen's doors
sense restraint and then that aversion
you're left with of that endurance
for what it is you just i'll be friendly
to it
that's where you'll start with yourself
and then if through that state you think
of others you'll be friendly to any
internal or external any shape or form
any perception of a version that appears
i'll be friendly to it i will sustain
the mind of friendliness
that's all i'm that unprotect that
anything that comes to it and goes
internally externally internally and
externally i shall sustain the mind of friendliness
i shall sustain the mind of friendliness
that's my concern
not to spread love to you just to not
lose the mind of friendliness in regard
to any patiga that comes my way
and whenever you search the suitors you
will see that how to deal with batiga
loving kindness mata yeah essentially
essentially but it's not like sure uh ill will
but it's not like sure uh ill will
towards others is a form of fatigue
but that's not particularly you you must
have been well restrained before that
your mind should have been withdrawn if
you're particularly concerned with
hating this person that person
to do brahman hara properly they would
culminate in opeca
because like you the monk the diligent
monk um sense restraint uh virtue sense
um sense restraint uh virtue sense
restraining gaza sends those then he
abandons he doesn't cultivate he doesn't
welcome thoughts of sensuality or
central desires doesn't entertain
doesn't psychologize
why i hate or why have these thoughts no
he simply does not
give any attention to those thoughts
until they are subdued so
thoughts of sensuality thoughts of
cruelty harm your will he subsumed
then thoughts about his reputation
concern about his reputation
thoughts about his his home country or
clans like
these kind of higher extensions of self
that everybody carries you know but that
is hard to see me and
what i think he he submutes that as well
not how long he justifies it or he
thinks about it he subdues that
so he refuses to engage with these
thoughts and then what he's left with
is the nature of things that's another
suit that says that
so it's not like all these things will
fall off as no he makes the effort to
not engage with them because they'll try
to hook you you know thoughts of
centrality we want you to think about it
even in terms of asuba you still accepted
in terms of asuba you still accepted
sensuality as a desire of a fact they
now try to get rid of it by thinking
it's super
thoughts of cruelty will try to hook you
to take them so to practice your
brahmavihara as in try to get rid of it that's not
as in try to get rid of it that's not
hara
so you need to be left with the clarity
of that endurance that you
inevitably going to be averse to how
much to that depends on how much
sensuality you had carried from before
and then ah it's the pure fatigue of
this experience internally externally that i
experience internally externally that i
should just be friendly towards and if
you're friendly to the fatigue of your
senses you'll be friendly to anybody
that comes through it
even if people come and beat you up and
abuse you you cannot hate because you
cannot abandon the doorway
of friendliness towards this through
which all of this manifests for you
so that's why truly like matter practice
will free you from all the batiga and
result in opaquer
and if it's if it's on that level
through sense restraint and watchfulness
and guiding of the sense those you could
just decide to be friendly towards
that there was this aversion and sustain
the friendliness regardless of the
aversion and aversion will
subdue be subdued in the same sense if
you choose to
sustain the knowledge of breeding
underneath your experience so to speak
breathing in breathing out
uh your thoughts will be subdued they
will be calmed down
you don't need to how do i know if i
stick to this
knowledge that i'm reading and reading
out while it is happening or whatever
else knowledge that breath is underneath
knowledge that breath is underneath
there happening to me in and out
in and out and i don't completely lose
the sight of it thoughts will be subdued
that's just the natural outcome of it
same sustain the friendliness towards
yourself in that sense of having been fully
in that sense of having been fully
restrained experiencing fatigue of the
sense restraint
just friendly towards that nothing else
and latiga will subdue
i mean in the in the rahula
again that i was mentioning after that
subduing of petiga
he then says developed a nietzsche
to get rid of well that's the
declaration seeing things clearly
you won't be seeing the clear true
meaning of that in each of that thing
because just to averse towards it
so you subdue your aversion what you're
left is
neither of us certainly not no no
central desire
and then oh let me make the effort and
see there's arisen on its own
inaccessible not mine what is it to
describe but the clarity is there
clarity well exactly on the kind of
clarity that you're not interfering with
your aversion now
you get to specify aspects of it that
you want to see such as a nietzsche
dukkha and then the experience is fully
going to be cessation of all the traces
of conceit and then
he's and then the buddha actually after
that then he starts to teach the
mindfulness of breathing the rest of the
mindfulness of breathing here that's
what i mean that's like the fulfillment
if you just then stick to that as a
practice if there are any traces
of any appropriation of any ignorance
left that you are kind of unaware of
that will also disappear if you stick to
that practice of that right order
breathing in in that
impersonal sense being unable to
experience a version anymore because you
have subdued it
no central desire and certainly no
appropriation because then perception
for nature has been fully developed
um because there were you know many like
like anagami's in case they had
so like little traces of egypt left that
even the buddha could not specifically
say where and how
he would just say if there is there
might be some residue and if there is
there will be you know
non-return and so on so that's why like
even if you think you're an argument
complete finished
just stick to that practice because it's
pleasant here and now
cultivate dana panasanti to that
fulfillment as he said to venerable
arita and then
if there were any traces that would be
that they would have been dealt with
by sticking to the practice of calming
correctly
so it's a win-win in other words even if
you were even if you're not honey win
because it's a pleasant abiding here and
now and if you're not an iron hunt you win
and if you're not an iron hunt you win
because it's a pleasant buzzing here now
and it frees you from anything that was
preventing you to be another hunt
and yeah but there's no breathing there
all that work you know where's the
breathing where's the breathing that you there's
where's the breathing that you there's
also
other work that you're doing you know
you're calming the fatigue
you're contemplating this breathing is
that just peripheral
recollection the knowledge of the breath
and during a beneath that's basically
the reference point that prevents you
from uh being uh to engage from your personal
uh being uh to engage from your personal
point of view
which you're contemplating because if
you're rooted in
a naturally occurring breath underneath
your experience breathing and bringing
out and refuse to give give up give that
and refuse to give give up give that
basis up basically you refuse to give
and that's already an impersonal
reference point that in personal
reference points
that's why you that's why eventually if
you stick to it everything else will be
seen through the impersonal reference
point not mine that's exactly what not mine is
not mine that's exactly what not mine is
in person so when you contemplate the
elements where you can't play
through the personal basis of breathing
enduring there you're contemplating it
rightly on that one through that impersonal
on that one through that impersonal
basis of that thing which is so
personal so sure sure so close to you
yes that's why
it's a useful and suitable reference
point because you could take other
references reference points but they will be
reference points but they will be
exactly
sooner or later you end up appropriating
them so then it ceases to be an
impersonal reference point through which
you get to see all this
personality and so on that's going on
emotions and moods and
and that's principles
in personal reference to which you will
purify everything from your gratuitous
sense of personality
that's why it's for the one way for
purification of beings there's nothing
else to result in
stick to satipattanas and it would
purify beings of
personality i arranged
in any in every shape or form no matter
how lingering how subtle
if you do it sufficiently enough and
anapanasati is the fulfillment of for satipatanos
is the fulfillment of for satipatanos
nothing else
that's not suitable